<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon two pamphlets lately published one called, A letter from Monsieur de Cros, concerning the memoirs of Christendom. And the other, An answer to that letter. Pretended to have been written by the author of the said memoirs. By a Lover of truth. Imprimatur, Edward Cooke. April 21st. 1693.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R734AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831975</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831975</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2132:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon two pamphlets lately published one called, A letter from Monsieur de Cros, concerning the memoirs of Christendom. And the other, An answer to that letter. Pretended to have been written by the author of the said memoirs. By a Lover of truth. Imprimatur, Edward Cooke. April 21st. 1693.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Baldwin, near the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: Reflections on a letter from Monsieur de Cros, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>"Reflections upon an answer to the letter from Mons. De Cros" has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Du Cros, Simon, 17th cent. --  Lettre de Monsieur Du Cross à Mylord **** afin de servir de réponse aux impostures de Monsieur le Chevalier Temple --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Temple, William, --  Sir, 1628-1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36442:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36442:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON TWO PAMPHLETS Lately Publiſhed; One called, A
LETTER from Monſieur <hi>de Cros,</hi> concerning the MEMOIRS of
<hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> And the Other, An ANSWER to that Letter. Pretended to
have been written by the Author of the ſaid MEMOIRS.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 21ſt.
1693.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>EDWARD COOKE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the
<hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36442:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36442:2"/>
                  <head>REFLECTIONS ON A LETTER From Monſieur <hi>de Cros,</hi>
&amp;c.</head>
                  <p>I Was very glad when I heard that one Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de
Cros</hi> had publiſhed an Anſwer to a late Book, Entituled, <hi>Memoirs of
what paſs'd in</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And could not but expect
ſome conſiderable Diſcoveries in thoſe Affairs and Intriegues, from a
perſon who thought himſelf a Match for Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> Beſides, I
hoped it might have had this good Effect, to move that Author in his own
defence to oblige us once more with his Pen. This was ſufficient to make me
buy this Pamphlet greedily, as I do moſt others; which tho very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten they
entertain one ill enough, yet ſerve in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for ſome amuſement
amidſt the Noiſe and Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a dirty Town.</p>
                  <p>But when I had read it over, I ſoon found my ſelf deceived
in the firſt; and have now loſt all hopes of the other, ſince I have
waited above two months in that Expectation, whereas two days were
ſufficient, had that Author thought fit to take any notice of ſuch a
Trifle, which makes me now deſpair of it; and as I perceiv'd the Town never
looked for any ſuch thing; ſo all I meet with, either in Coffee-houſes,
or Ordinary Converſation, have ſuch deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thoughts of this Letter,
that I now begin to find I never had any reaſon to expect it at all. For in
truth, the whole Letter ſeems to me only deſign'd <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36442:3"/>to
<hi>Banter</hi> Fools or Children, and to be written by a man who had loſt
all Reſpect to the Publick, whom he thinks fit to entertain with ſuch
wretched ſtuff, which certainly he could not pretend ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
pleaſe or inſtruct any Reader, who had not as much malice, and as little
Wit as himſelf. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Railing and Foul Language, his whole Letter
from the beginning to the end is an errant Sham and has nothing in it. 'Twas
therefore in vain to imagine Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> would deſcend ſo much below
himſelf, to take any notice of ſo fulſome a Libel; and I do not believe
either <hi>de Cros,</hi> or the kind Writer of the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement</hi>
after the Letter, did ever expect it.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, If Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> be ſuch a Philoſopher,
as he ſeems to be by his <hi>Eſſay upon the Gardens of</hi> Epicurus, as
well as ſeveral others; he muſt infinitely contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Ideas thoſe
Writings have given of him, if ſo ſordid and inſipid a Trifle as this
Letter of <hi>de Cros</hi> could have any power to provoke him, tho it were but
to ſcorn it.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, if he be ſo proud a Perſon, as <hi>De Cros</hi>
is pleaſed to call him; certainly, while he remembers his own Quality, and
the great Employments he has paſſed through with ſo much Honour to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſuch important Services for his Prince and Country, ſuch
thoughts will never allow him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Liſts with one; who to ſay no
more, has owned himſelf in his Letter to be <hi>Un Moin Defroquè,</hi>
which none who underſtand the leaſt of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, need be
told, is the loweſt and moſt profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Character that can be given a Man.
I ſuppoſe the reaſon of it is, becauſe he who has once broke his Vow to
God, there are People enough apt to believe he will never regard any he makes
to them.</p>
                  <p>A third Reaſon is, Becauſe his Letter is indeed
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable; and Proſecution would be as little neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to him, as
to one that pleads guilty at the Bar; for he owns over and over, every Line of
the Charge <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36442:3"/>that he pretends is laid againſt him; ſays not
one word, either to defend or extenuate it; does not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the leaſt
point in the Memoirs he pretends to Anſwer; nor lays one ill Action to Sir
<hi>W. T</hi>'s Honour. So that there remains but one way to Anſwer this
Letter with any Rule or Juſtice, and that is, to gather all the cleanly
Language one can pick up at <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> and bring it in its
natural Reeking to the Preſs, and ſo make up a ſhort, but ſweet
Pamphlet, ſet out with a Bead-roll of ſuch Pearls, as are always to be
found among the Oyſter-women.</p>
                  <p>A fourth Reaſon is, Becauſe that Book which goes by the
Name of Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s <hi>Memoirs,</hi> as one ſees by the
Publiſher's Preface, has been printed wholly without his Knowledg or
Conſent: For in the very firſt lines he plainly intimates he had his Copy
from no Man then alive: And a known Writer ſince, who pretends to have
inquired into that matter, aſſures us, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher had it lying by him
ſeveral years before it was publiſhed; nor can I find by my own beſt
Inquiries, that Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> has ever own'd it. And tho I may believe,
like others, that he muſt have writ them, by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Stile, that
ſtrength and clearneſs of Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as by that Spirit and
Genius which ſo brightly ſhines through the whole, and is peculiar to that
Author above others of his Age; and beſides, becauſe I ſuppoſe no Man
elſe was capable of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or diſcovering ſo much of theſe
Tranſactions; yet ſince they have ſtollen into Publick againſt his
will, and his privity, it is not to be imagined he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a thing he
does not reckon as his own; and therefore if <hi>de Cros,</hi> or the honeſt
<hi>Tranſlator,</hi> had found themſelves injured, their reſentments had
been more juſtly levelled at the Publiſher, than the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
Author.</p>
                  <p>By all theſe Reaſons, 'tis eaſy to believe, that a
Perſon of Sir <hi>W. T.</hi>'s Character and Honour, and whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
is ſo firmly eſtabliſhed in the World, will <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36442:4"/>never fall
ſo low to oppoſe himſelf againſt the Scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Reproaches of ſo
foul-mouth'd a Railer; 'twould be like a ſet Duel between a ſtrong Man
well-arm'd, and a poor wretched Cripple. The Quarrel therefore will be more
properly turn'd over to the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; for tho the venom of
<hi>this</hi> be too weak to reach where it aim'd; yet all thoſe who have any
regard for Truth or Juſtice, for Learning or Virtue, or even for good Manners
and common Civility, muſt think themſelves concern'd in a Quarrel, where
they find ſo notorious a breach of them all.</p>
                  <p>'Tis fit therefore ſo ignominious a Libeller ſhould be
expoſed in his proper Colours, of an infamous, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and unprovok't
Railer; which tho his own Letter has plentifully done, yet 'twill be very
proper to point to ſeveral places in it, where it is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</p>
                  <p>For my own part, I will confeſs, I have been a great Reader
of all Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s Writings, and perhaps may have doated on ſome of
them, eſpecially, <hi>That Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Eſſay on Heroick Virtue,</hi> as one
Writer ſince has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly called it; and that other upon
<hi>Poetry,</hi> and even on this of the <hi>Memoirs.</hi> And finding Common
Fame, wherever I had met it, agrees ſo well with the Picture theſe Pieces
had given me of him, I will own to have had a very great Honour for the Author,
as well as for his Books, and could not but eſteem both a great deal the more
for this Letter of <hi>de Cros,</hi> when I found that the triple-corded Malice
of the <hi>Writer,</hi> the <hi>Tranſlator,</hi> and the
<hi>Advertiſer,</hi> had not given one laſh either to the Honour of the
Perſon, or the truth of his Books. And all this put together, has in very
truth given me ſo much Spight and Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I could not refrain
entring on the <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phletiers</hi> Trade, which I never did before, nor ever
thought I ſhould have done at all: And but for this Provocation, could have
been very well ſatisfied to have lived on without the itch of ſeeing how I
look <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36442:4"/>in Print; ſo that I may truly ſay for this, as the
Poet does for his Verſes, 
<q> 
                        <l>
                           <hi>— Facit Indignatio Verſus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before I enter upon obſerving what <hi>de Cros</hi> ſays
concerning Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> which takes up the greateſt part of his Letter,
and leaves him either no Room, or no Memory for the <hi>Memoirs</hi> he
pretends to Anſwer; I ſhall firſt examine what he ſpeaks of himſelf,
and in his own defence, againſt what he takes himſelf to be charged
with.</p>
                  <p>He begins, p. 10. <hi>There arrived</hi> (ſays he, quoting
the <hi>Memoirs) at that time from</hi> England, <hi>one whoſe Name was</hi>
de Cros. Upon this he falls immediately into a Scurrilous Chafe. Now, one would
wonder what ſhould make the Man ſo offended to be called by his own Name,
or what would have become of Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> if he had call'd him out of his
Name, which is indeed commonly thought an injury, but not the other, as ever I
heard of before; yet he reckons it a terrible one to himſelf and his Family,
which he tells us is <hi>a good one;</hi> I know not whether he means the
<hi>de Cros</hi>'s, or the <hi>Monks.</hi> The firſt I muſt confeſs, I
never heard of in <hi>France,</hi> but the other is indeed a great one abroad,
and a good one at home. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he would have us think of the Goodneſs
of his Family, I will never believe, by what little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I have of
Heraldry, that any <hi>Gentleman</hi> would either write ſuch a Letter, or
<hi>Tranſlate</hi> it, tho it were only out of the common Reſpect that is
due to the Memory of a Great King, whoſe Perſon Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> has ſo
often repreſented, and in ſo high a Character.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed; <hi>That he was formerly a</hi> French
<hi>Monk</hi> (as the Memoirs call him), he confeſſes, and owns beſides
(tho with a great deal of ill-will) that <hi>He changed his Frock for a
Petticoat:</hi> For, tho he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36442:5"/>it poſitively,
<hi>p.</hi> 11. yet five Lines after, he has theſe words; <hi>There was too
great advantage to throw off my Frock for the Petticoat I have taken, not to do
it; it is a Petticoat of a</hi> Scotch <hi>Stuff,</hi> &amp;c. I am glad it is
of one ſo good as he mentions, and wiſh it were large enough to cover all
his Shame: But whatever he ſays in the ſame Page, too malicious to be taken
notice of here, of <hi>Princeſſes, who have quitted the Veil for the
Breeches</hi> (tho, in that it ſelf, I believe, he is miſtaken) yet all
this will never ſerve to wipe off the Ignominy of <hi>Un Moin
Defroquè:</hi> Upon which I ſhall only add, That the Marriage of a
Monk, when ſtripp'd of his Frock, is not thought likely to mend the matter:
And I believe men of all Religions will agree in the Opinion, That if a Monk
leaves his Frock, he ought to do it for a <hi>Gown,</hi> rather than for a
<hi>Petticoat;</hi> and if he leaves the Orders of one Church, ſhould in
decency continue in the Orders of that Church to which he profeſſes
himſelf converted.</p>
                  <p>As to his being a <hi>Swediſh Agent,</hi> tho he is very
angry the <hi>Memoirs</hi> ſhould call him ſo; one cannot well diſcover
by his Letter, whether he has a mind to grant it of no; however, he
confeſſes, p. 13, 14. That <hi>being Envoy from the Duke of</hi>
Holſtein-Gottorp, <hi>the Intereſts of his Maſter being inſeperable
from thoſe of</hi> Sueden, <hi>he found himſelf engaged to be very much
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Intereſts of that Crown; and that Monſieur</hi> Van
Beuninguen <hi>believed, He was intruſted with ſome Affairs from
thence.</hi> Which amounts to the very ſame with what the <hi>Memoirs</hi>
ſay, p. 335. That <hi>he</hi> (de Cros) <hi>had a Commiſſion from the
Court of</hi> Sueden <hi>(or Credence at leaſt) for a certain petty Agency
in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. This he ſays, <hi>Is very Dirty.</hi> Alas for the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Gentleman! one would think he was afraid of fouling his Fingers, but he had a
great deal more need have taken care of his mouth. By the way, I cannot but
admire at the inſufferable Impudence of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Printer or
Tranſlator, who hath in the Title Page <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36442:5"/>named this man,
<hi>An Ambaſſador at the Treaty of</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meguen; ſince in the ſeveral
Accounts I have ſeen printed of that Treaty, there is not the leaſt
menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a Name any other way than in thoſe <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs</hi> he
pretends to Anſwer. And 'tis doubt leſs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry agreeable to think, that a
man who gives himſelf ſo <hi>good</hi> a Character in his own Letter,
ſhould make ſo great a one in ſo Auguſt an Aſſembly as that is
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to have been: And he himſelf in his whole Letter, arrogates no
other beſides that of Envoy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary from the Duke of
<hi>Holſtein-Gottorp</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> who was a Prince at that
time wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd of His Dominions.</p>
                  <p>Another Paſſage in the Memoirs which he takes ſadly to
heart, is in the ſame <hi>Pag.</hi> 335. as follows: <hi>At</hi> London
<hi>he had devoted himſelf wholly to Monſieur</hi> Barillon, <hi>the</hi>
French <hi>Ambaſſador, though pretending to purſue the Intereſts
of</hi> Sweden: Againſt which he thus defends himſelf. Firſt, Letter,
<hi>pag.</hi> 14. He abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely denies it; and ſays in the next, <hi>He
fell out with Monſieur</hi> Barillon <hi>for three Months, becauſe he
diverted the King of</hi> England <hi>from taking into his conſideration the
Intereſts of</hi> Sweden. And <hi>pag.</hi> 16. He ſays fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>That
Monſieur</hi> Barillon <hi>put all in practice to ſift him to the
bottom</hi> (concerning the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Affairs) <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs all
the Offers of this Ambaſſador proved inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, and wrought nothing upon
this man</hi> (meaning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>who if a man would give credit to
Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>was entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly devoted to Monſieur</hi> Barillon, <hi>and
yet Monſieur</hi> Barillon <hi>found him not to be corrupted or bribed.</hi>
All this would be an Account good enough of his Innocence in that point, if it
had not the misfortune to be ſo ill plac'd. 'Tis indeed a good way back to
the fifth Page of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And therefore what he ſays there, one may by
the help of a little Charity, impute to the ſhortneſs of his Memory.
Theſe are his Words: <hi>I have had the happineſs during ſome years, to
partake in the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a Miniſter of State,</hi> &amp;c. And a little
after; <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36442:6"/>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>may well imagine that I did
not ill improve this able Miniſter's Confidence, when he tells us, that I had
wholly devoted my ſelf to him.</hi> But then how comes it, that in the ſame
15<hi>th</hi> page, where he twice endeavours to defend himſelf againſt
this Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſhould make ſuch a Blunder as to ſay, <hi>But yet I
muſt confeſs, that at ſuch time as he</hi> (<hi>Monſieur</hi>
Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillon) <hi>ſtickled for my Maſter's Intereſt, and that of</hi>
Sweden, <hi>I was</hi> entirely devoted <hi>to him,</hi> &amp;c.? After this,
let the Reader judge, whether <hi>de Cros</hi> does not confeſs at leaſt as
much, if not more in this Point, than the Memoirs charge him with: And it is to
be obſerved from the ſame Book, that at the very time <hi>de Cros</hi>
ſpeaks of, <hi>France</hi> had taken into its Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Intereſts of
<hi>Sweden,</hi> which it ſeem'd for ſome Months before to have very little
regarded.</p>
                  <p>But nothing touches him ſo nearly as the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Paſſage in the ſame 335<hi>th</hi> page of the Memoirs: <hi>This man
brought me a Pacquet from Court, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding me to go immediately away to</hi>
Nimeguen. Upon which, ſays he, <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. <hi>Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>has a
mind to make men believe that I was only ſent into</hi> Holland <hi>to carry
him a Diſpatch from the Court.</hi> This paſſage has ſo fiercely gall'd
him, that he is ſet a railing for ſix pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together; and the affront is,
that he ſhould be taken for an ordinary Courier, or Meſſenger. Had a
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Waſps ſetled on his Tongue, they could not have ſwell'd or infus'd
more Poiſon in it; he frets and foams at the mouth, and ſpatters ſo much
Dirt on all ſides, that it is not ſafe following him. In ſhort, he takes
it ſo heinouſly to be reckoned a Common Courier, that one could not have
netled him more, had one call'd him a Poſt, or a Poſt-horſe. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
imagine why any ſuch words in the <hi>Memoirs,</hi> ſhould put a man into
ſo much paſſion: And for my part, both in this and all the reſt, I
ſee but one reaſon why he is angry; and that is, <hi>Becauſe he is
angry.</hi> However, againſt this grievous Imputation, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36442:6"/>he
defends himſelf by this ſtrong Argument; That <hi>he was not ſent over on
purpoſe to deliver the Diſpatch to Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>but for ſomething
of greater importance, which he knows himſelf, and will not tell any
body.</hi> Wherein I think he acts very diſcreetly; and I do not doubt, but
the beſt way to give any Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his mighty Secrets, is to hinder them
from taking Air: Tho had he done us the favour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover but one of all
thoſe he boaſts ſo much of, it would perhaps have been the moſt
effectual way to raiſe our expectation of the reſt. He would indeed make us
believe, that in five Hours time he ſtay'd at the <hi>Hague,</hi> he had made
ſome mighty Turn of State by his Negotiations there; which if there be any
truth in it, we will grant him to have been not only an <hi>Agent,</hi> but a
<hi>Conjurer;</hi> and from the ſtrange Effect of his Conduct in that
ſtrange <hi>Adventure of five hours,</hi> we may hope one day to ſee a
<hi>Tragedy of that Name,</hi> as there has been a <hi>Comedy</hi> already. But
till he thinks fit to make more important Diſcoveries, he will pardon our
ſuſpenſe in that modeſt Opinion he had of himſelf, That doubtleſs
he ſhould publiſh more juſt and ſolid <hi>Memoirs</hi> than Sir <hi>W.
T.</hi> if he would ſet about it. But I obſerve he deſires <hi>My Lord to
take notice, that Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>confeſſes it was</hi> De Cros
<hi>procured this Diſpatch.</hi> I find when men are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry, that Truth
is the leaſt thing they regard: For this is more than ever I could obſerve
after reading thoſe <hi>Memoirs</hi> with more care and applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than I
am ſure his good humour would ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him; and in <hi>pag.</hi> 336.
find theſe Words: <hi>How this Diſpatch by</hi> De Cros <hi>was gain'd, or
by whom, I will not pretend to determine.</hi> Which <hi>De Cros</hi> has very
politickly thus altered, <hi>Letter, pag.</hi> 18. <hi>I will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to
determine by what means, and how</hi> De Cros <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this
Diſpatch.</hi> But <hi>pag.</hi> 19. he forgets himſelf again, and ſays.
<hi>As for me, tho I had the diſpatch gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, yet he</hi> (<hi>Sir</hi> W.
T.) <hi>does not accuſe me openly in <pb n="12" facs="tcp:36442:7"/>this place of bearing
any other part in this affair, that only as a Meſſenger intruſted with
the Conveyance.</hi> But I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he never looked farther than his malice
would give him leave, which is uſually very ſhort-ſighted.</p>
                  <p>But after all, 'tis not eaſily thought why he ſhould lay
it ſo much to heart to be called a Courier, when the whole account he gives
of his great Negotiations (beſides his being Envoy of the <hi>Duke</hi> of
<hi>Holſtein-Gottorp</hi>) is, that he <hi>was ſent by King</hi> Charles
<hi>the Second into</hi> Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>and</hi> Denmark, <hi>to haſten the
Paſſports for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs at</hi> Nimeguen: Which is all he tells us of
his great Employments, and muſt be thought to have brought him into that
intimacy and confidence he pretends with that great King, and for which he is
pleaſed to make his Majeſty ſuch grateful Returns, and to form ſuch a
Character of him as he does in his Letter.</p>
                  <p>For in the firſt place he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 5. That
<hi>Monſ.</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillon <hi>was the</hi> Primum Mobile <hi>of that King's
conduct, which ſurprized all the World.</hi> Which is to affirm more of him
than any of his diſcontented Subjects, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Patriots of that Age.
For it is to aſſert open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and poſitively what they only pretended to
ſuſpect.</p>
                  <p>Again, Soon after the King had made the Peace with
<hi>Holland, De Cros</hi> brings his Majeſty in, <hi>p.</hi> 23. ſpeaking
to him in theſe Words: <hi>Tell the King my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (meaning the
<hi>French</hi> King) <hi>that it is much againſt my mind, that I have made
peace with theſe</hi> Coquins <hi>the</hi> Hollanders. And then a little
before the concluſion of the Peace at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> he delivers the King
ſpeaking thus to Monſ. <hi>Shrenburn</hi> concerning the <hi>Hollanders; In
a little time Monſieur, I will bring theſe</hi> Coquins <hi>to
Reaſon.</hi> And in the ſame page he makes that Prince uſe the ſame
Name to two great Miniſters, Monſ. <hi>Barillon,</hi> and Monſ. <hi>De
Avaux.</hi> The former whereof he pretends to have been the firſt Mover of
all His Majeſty's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. All which, if they be not abſolute Untruths,
as from his plentiful Gift that way, I am very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36442:7"/>to believe, yet are ſo far from ſhewing the
<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reſpect</hi> the Writer pretends to, for the Memory of that
Prince, that being put together, they make up this malicious Character; That a
King of <hi>England</hi> was guided in his Conduct by a <hi>French</hi>
Embaſſador; That he made and obſerved his Treaties with ill-meaning, or
with ill-intentions; and that he treated his chiefeſt Confident (whom he
makes to be Monſ. <hi>Barillon</hi>) and another Embaſſador, with the
greateſt ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, he brings this noble Prince upon the Stage, acting
a mean piece of Diſſimulation to cover his Confidence with ſo worthy a
Perſon as Monſ. <hi>de Cros;</hi> 'tis concerning his Diſpatch ſo often
mentioned into <hi>Holland;</hi> for being forc't to confeſs, that the King
was angry with him at his return from thence; He plaiſters it up with
ſaying, p. 25. <hi>If the late King of</hi> England <hi>did not approve of my
Conduct in the Affairs of</hi> Nimeguen, <hi>which in effect he declared in
publick not to be pleaſed with, in which he plaid his part to
admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But ſince we have ſeen the Character he gives of him as a
King, let us obſerve how he Treats His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as a <hi>Mediator,</hi> and
how he Repreſents him bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing the Affairs of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> then
in his hands. Firſt, <hi>de Cros</hi> tells us, This Diſpatch of his
<hi>was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed with Monſieur</hi> Barillon: For tho he ſays, That that
Ambaſſadour had no had in the beginning of it, yet he owns him in the
ſame place to <hi>have part of it when it was concluding;</hi> and that
<hi>Monſieur</hi> de Ruvig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>was diſpatcht by the King with an Account
of it to the</hi> French <hi>Court the very ſame day that</hi> de Cros
<hi>was ſent away for</hi> Nimeguen. And <hi>p.</hi> 25. He tells us further,
That <hi>Prince</hi> Rupert <hi>askt him upon his Return, with a ſtern
Countenance, If the Peace was concluded? and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering in the
Affirmative, the Prince cried out, O Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation!</hi> And <hi>p.</hi>
28. he tells us, That the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange (the Kings Nephew) <hi>writ
thundring Letters <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36442:8"/>againſt him; and all the Miniſters of
the Confederates called for Vengeance,</hi> &amp;c. Yet after all theſe Marks
of ſomething ſo very injurious to the <hi>Allies,</hi> and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to
<hi>France, The King</hi> (ſays he, in the page laſt mentioned) <hi>laughs
in his Sleeve at the Surprize, at the Sorrow, and Complaints of the
Confederates.</hi> Which is to give us juſt ſuch a Character of a
<hi>Mediator,</hi> as he did before of a <hi>King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I leave it to all mens Judgment, whether more vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous
Slanders could have been broached abroad by the worſt of this Prince's
Enemies; and whether it be not a Scandal to our Country, that they ſhould be
tranſlated and publiſhed in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But ſince Monſieur
<hi>de Cros</hi> is ſo bold with the Sacred Memory of a Great King, for which
he is yet ſo Impudent, as to profeſs <hi>a moſt profound Reſpect;</hi>
What can a <hi>Subject</hi> expect, for whom he owns ſuch a virulent Malice,
and to whom he threatens ſuch open Revenge.</p>
                  <p>The ſame vein of truth and ſincerity ſhines through the
whole Letter, and the Author's Ingenuity is at the old pitch in what he
pretends to rake out of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs</hi> concerning ſeveral Perſons in
great Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as the D. of <hi>Lauder dale,</hi> the preſent E. of
<hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Joſeph Williamſon,</hi> Sir <hi>Lionel
Jenkins,</hi> and Monſ. <hi>Beverning.</hi> This <hi>Conjurer,</hi> in all he
ſays of them, ſeems reſolved to raiſe up the Spirits of the Dead, to
joyn with thoſe of the Living in the Quarrel with theſe <hi>Memoirs;</hi>
and by ſuch diſtorted Conſequences, draws Characters of them, whereof
there is no Apparition, but what he himſelf raiſes: So that the Characters
he gives of theſe Perſons by ſuch falſe Deductions for Sir <hi>W.
T</hi>'s, may juſtly be ſaid to be his own.</p>
                  <p>But from all I have obſerved in this Letter, I have wonder'd
at nothing ſo much, as that impudent Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the Writer, who endeavours to
make himſelf and the World believe, that theſe <hi>Memoirs</hi> were
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended chiefly againſt him, whoſe very name is hardly twice mentioned
after theſe two Pages in the whole <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36442:8"/>Book, which does not
pretend to give Characters of Perſons, but only to relate things that were
done, or words that were ſaid; And the way to have made an anſwer with any
Juſtice, had been to have laid Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions either againſt the one, or the
other, whereof there is not one word in all this <hi>Anſwer without any
Anſwer.</hi> However, ſo ridiculous is this mans Inſolence, that he
begins his Letter thus, <hi>I have been informed of the Calumnies that Sir</hi>
W. T. <hi>hath cauſed to be printed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> And p. 7. <hi>He
ſet upon me firſt, he writes out of a Spirit of Revenge,</hi> &amp;c. The
ſenſleſs Arrogance of which I cannot think of; but it remembers me of the
Fly on the Chariot-wheel. For he would fain make it to have been a piece of
Revenge againſt him, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought that Diſpatch to the
<hi>Hague;</hi> and yet he lays it much to heart, that in that Affair he
ſhould only take him for a <hi>Meſſenger.</hi> And this indeed is to make
him a very reaſonable perſon, and like a man, that when he receives a blow,
grows angry with the Stone by which it is given. But by all I can obſerve in
theſe <hi>Memoirs,</hi> I do not find any thing which bears the leaſt
reſemblance of Anger or Spleen, much leſs of Revenge againſt Monſ.
<hi>de Cros;</hi> but ſo far from it, that in the very Paſſage he lays
moſt to heart, of the Kings calling him <hi>Rogue,</hi> the <hi>Memoirs</hi>
mention particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that His Majeſty ſaid it <hi>pleaſantly,</hi>
which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf cannot forbear obſerving in his Letter.</p>
                  <p>Having thus long been conſidering how far he is provok'd,
and how well he defends himſelf; 'tis time now to ſee how he attacks the
Perſon whom he fancies his capital Enemy, and how the Play begins. 'Tis then
in theſe words, <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>I know very well that Sir</hi> W. T.
<hi>is of great worth, and deſerves well, and that he hath been a long time
imployed, and that too upon important Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> This is a piece indeed
very much of a piece with all the reſt. Now, in the name of wonder, what can
be the meaning! I wot well enough, what he would be at in all the reſt of his
Letter; but the Senſe, the Wit, <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36442:9"/>or the Deſign of theſe
ſweet Lines, is not eaſy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe. I confeſs, I ſee a good many
Plays, and I believe I have read more, but never met before, ſo fair a
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to ſo foul a Farce. I have read ſomewhere of a Monſter among
the Ancients, with a Virgins face, and all beſide, a Serpent; which holds
exact Reſemblance here, unleſs <hi>de Cros</hi> ſhould object againſt
it, becauſe Serpents have ſtings, and his Letter has none. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if we
will not grant him a <hi>Conjurer,</hi> as he would fain be thought, yet we
cannot in Conſcience deny him to be a <hi>Jugler,</hi> ſince the firſt
thing he preſents us with, is meer <hi>ſlight of hand;</hi> For he lays
down a piece of <hi>Gold</hi> upon the Table, and immediately, <hi>Preſto,
'tis gone;</hi> and all we can ſee, is only half a dozen Pellets of
<hi>Dirt.</hi> In ſhort, I am not able to reach what he means by ſo
whimſical a beginning, and of ſo different a piece from every word that
follows; unleſs that being reſolved to ſay nothing afterwards, which any
body would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he thought fit to entertain us at firſt with three Lines
he is ſure no body doubts.</p>
                  <p>But, to be ſerious. If Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> be <hi>of great
worth,</hi> If <hi>de Cros</hi> either believes it himſelf, or would have any
body elſe to do ſo, why is every word that follows, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to
theſe? If he <hi>deſerves well,</hi> why is he uſed ſo very ill? Does
<hi>de Cros</hi> underſtand what a man of <hi>great worth</hi> means? I doubt
he does not, either by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by ſuch Company, as ſo much good
Language in all the reſt of his Letter, would make us believe he keeps. Can a
man <hi>of great worth,</hi> and that <hi>deſerves well,</hi> be <hi>Vain,
Proud, Revengeful, Ungrateful to his Friend, Falſe to his Maſter,</hi> and
impertinently <hi>Ambitious</hi> in his very Retreat from all Publick Affairs?
This is indeed a very worthy, and a very lively Character of a Man <hi>of
worth.</hi> But is not ſuch ſtuff as this, juſt a ſputtering out,
<hi>Quicquid in Buccam venerit?</hi> Like hot Porridge that burns his Tongue;
tho 'tis pretty plain, that all his heat proceeds from the overflowing of his
Gall within, and from nothing without. One would think <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36442:9"/>he
has very well practiſed the old Rule of <hi>Calumniare fortiter;</hi> yet he
has lamentably fail'd of the conſequence, <hi>Aliquid inherebit;</hi> for all
the Dirt he endeavours to fling about, loves its own Element, and ſticks
cloſe to his own Fingers. I never knew ſo unlucky a Gameſter to throw
ſo often, and to be always out! What, not one hit! I think the devil's in the
Dice; however, lets throw again, but firſt we'll change Dice, and if the good
Morals of this Man of great worth will not paſs, let's try our luck at his
Naturals. Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> (ſays my Gameſter) <hi>has been often and long
employ'd;</hi> but he himſelf did <hi>not know about what,</hi> 'twas too,
<hi>upon very important occaſions,</hi> but he did <hi>not know why,</hi>
unleſs; becauſe, as <hi>de Cros</hi> tells us, <hi>The King had an
Averſion for him, and never truſted him,</hi> how often ſoever he
imployed him. This great Ambaſſador. to ſay the truth, is a very
<hi>Bubble,</hi> and has as little Wit in ſome parts of the Letter, as
Honeſty in the other Good Lord, how this ſilly World is apt to be gull'd!
What a Cheat, and what a Jilt this common Fame is! Who would have believed that
the Author of the <hi>Obſervations on the</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, and of the
charming <hi>Miſcellanea,</hi> ſhould be ſuch a Cully, if <hi>de
Cros</hi> had not made the diſcovery? but ſure he could never be Author of
thoſe Books; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he either hired ſome body to write them for him,
or elſe ſome honeſt-Bookſeller like his own, had got the Copies, and
ſet Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s name to them. <hi>I would to God he had been ſo
honeſt to ſet mine in the ſtead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But not we have heard the Charge, pray make room for the
Evidence: Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> is the <hi>proudeſt Man</hi> in the World; and
what are the proofs, or the Inſtances? Why, <hi>de Cros</hi> ſays it, and
that's Demonſtration. He is ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to his Friend, and why? Becauſe
<hi>de Cros</hi> knows it. He is falſe to his Maſter, and the Reaſon's
plain, <hi>de Cros</hi> pretends to believe it. He is <hi>the moſt revengeful
of-Men,</hi> for he calls <hi>de Cros</hi> by his <hi>own Name.</hi> He is of
all men <hi>the moſt Ambitious,</hi> and <hi>never did man deſire more to
have a hand in Affairs.</hi> This is beyond diſpute, for <hi>de Cros</hi>
knows his thoughts, and tells us not only what he <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36442:10"/>ſays of
others, but what he thinks of himſelf, and with equal truth. This is the
<hi>Conjurer</hi> again, and with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he tells us further, <hi>p.</hi>
9. of men <hi>whoſe ruin Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>deſires at the bottom of his
heart;</hi> where it is not to be queſtioned, but <hi>de Cros</hi> has been;
and to put it beyond all doubt that he was ſo, he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 13.
That <hi>Sir</hi> W. T. <hi>came once to render</hi> him <hi>a viſit at</hi>
his <hi>Lodging,</hi> and that <hi>Monſ.</hi> Olivencrants <hi>the</hi>
Swediſh <hi>Ambaſſador, was then at</hi> his <hi>Houſe,</hi> which
gives me a ſcruple, that the viſit might be meant to <hi>him,</hi> rather
than to Monſ. <hi>de Cros.</hi> However this is all the inſtances I find of
his Acquaintance with a Perſon whoſe heart he pretends to know ſo well,
and with whom by all the reſt of his Letter, I ſhould be apt to judge he
was the leaſt acquainted with, of any man in the World. But to cloſe all
theſe Generals before we come to particulars; he tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 29. he
knows ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> upon the Subject of what paſſed
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and my Lord <hi>Arlington, that makes</hi> his <hi>hair ſtand an
end.</hi> Alas, the poor Gentleman's in an Agony! Bleſs us all from
ſprights! what a puny Conjurer is this! to raiſe a Spirit that ſcares no
body elſe, and run into a hole for fear of it himſelf: He has formed ſo
terrible an Image of Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> in his own little working Noddle, that
he knows not were he is, nor what he does, but is all in a maze. However, this
I am certain, that no man alive who has read the reſt of <hi>de Cros</hi>'s
Letter, but will allow him to be one, that if he knew any thing ill of Sir
<hi>W. T.</hi> would at leaſt be ſure not to tell it; we have his own word
for it, p. 7. <hi>My deſign is not at all, my Lord, to write you a Letter
full of Invectives againſt Sir</hi> W. T. And in another place, <hi>That</hi>
(ſays he) <hi>would not be like a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But yet to give him his due, and as he ſays, p. 7. <hi>To
let everybody ſee</hi> he <hi>has means in</hi> his <hi>hands to be
revenged;</hi> there is one point, and that alone, where he brings his Proof,
lays downs his Inſtance, and that out of the <hi>Memoirs</hi> themſelves;
'tis deſigned undeniably to convince the World of Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s Vanity,
of which he could give <hi>my <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36442:10"/>Lord</hi> many inſtances,
but at preſent contents himſelf with one, and 'tis a thumping one. 'Tis the
following Period, which I ſhall quote out of the <hi>Memoirs,</hi> a little
more faithfully than he does in his Letter, which I was ſo curious to
obſerve, by thinking the word <hi>[Clutches]</hi> to be no part of Sir <hi>W.
T</hi>'s ſtile, and found he had taken a great deal of pains, to wreſt it
as much as he could to his turn. It runs thus, <hi>Mem.</hi> p. 30. <hi>This I
ſuppoſe gave ſome occaſion for my being again deſigned for this
Ambaſſy, who was thought to have ſome credit with</hi> Spain <hi>as well
as</hi> Holland, <hi>from the Negotiations I had formerly run through at
the</hi> Hague, Bruſſels, <hi>and</hi> Aix la Chapelle, <hi>by which the
remaining part of</hi> Flanders <hi>had been ſaved out of the hands of</hi>
France <hi>in the year</hi> 1668. Now for my own part, I muſt confeſs my
ſelf ſo giddy a Reader, and of ſo much inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency, that when I read
that Paſſage, I took it for a ſingular piece of Modeſty, ſince the
Author gives for a Reaſon, why the King choſe him for his ſecond
Ambaſſy in <hi>Holland,</hi> becauſe he had been formerly employed in
thoſe Countries, and not for any Perſonal Merit in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but <hi>de
Cros</hi> is ſo great a Stranger to Modeſty, that we cannot blame him for
not knowing it when he meets it; and ſince he has no other Accuſations of
this kind, I muſt profeſs, I can diſcover nothing of Vanity in the whole
<hi>Series</hi> of all thoſe Relations, nor can reckon for ſuch, the
Author's not avoiding to ſpeak of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf any more than of other Perſons
(when it came in his way) who had ſo great and ſo continual a part in the
whole Courſe of that Story. In his other Works this Author I am ſure makes
little mention enough of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and it were to be wiſht that Perſons
ſo much em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in publick Buſineſs, would tell all their own Parts as
well others Mens, and as nakedly as he ſeems to do in theſe
<hi>Memoirs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the reaſon <hi>de Cros</hi> gives us, why he would have
the World believe him in all he ſays againſt Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> is,
Becauſe he is firſt attackt, and thereupon in great Paſſion and Rage,
which will paſs for an admirable Argument, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36442:11"/>that he
deſigns to ſpeak nothing but truth, and for a very cunning way of being
believed; tho ſome men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may think, that whatever is ſaid in
Paſſion, is but juſt ſo much of <hi>nothing to the purpoſe,</hi> and
that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly makes a man in what he ſays or does, not only as peeviſh
as a Waſp, but as blind as a Beetle. But if he will believe right or wrong,
why will not he believe in his turn? And why is not he contented to
<hi>Give</hi> as well as to <hi>Take?</hi> He will not allow that Sir <hi>W.
T.</hi> might ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times have been Secretary of State, when Mr.
<hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sydney,</hi> who are named (in <hi>Memoirs
p.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>_…</desc>
                     </gap>) to have been ſet on him by
the Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> at that time to perſuade him to accept it, are
ſtill alive, as well as my Lord Treaſurer, who is mentioned, <hi>Mem.
p.</hi> 273. to have written to him by His Majeſty's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to come over
and enter on the Secretaries Office. And <hi>p.</hi> 385. 'tis further added,
That Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>King's own Orders to come immediately
over, and enter upon that Office, and to acquaint the Prince and States with
that Reſolution;</hi> which muſt of courſe have come to him through my
Lord <hi>Sunderland</hi>'s hand, who <hi>Mem. p.</hi> 387. is ſaid to have
been brought into Sir <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Williamſon</hi>'s place, and his
Lordſhip being likewiſe ſtill alive, can eaſily tell, whether this be
true or no. Therefore, why does not <hi>de Cros</hi> himſelf, or ſome
Friend for him (if he has any) enquire into the truth of theſe Paſſages
which are told ſo poſitively, and wherein ſo many parties concern'd are
ſtill alive, tho moſt of them with other Titles. And indeed, tho it may be
ill for Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s private Satisfaction, that theſe <hi>Memoirs</hi>
were printed againſt his Conſent, and during his Life, which it appears was
never intended; yet nothing could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Truth of them ſo much, as that
ſo many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are yet alive, who had ſo great a part in all thoſe
Affairs there related, who are the beſt and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges of the
Truth; and I never heard that any of them have yet contradicted the leaſt
part. But however, ſince the <hi>Monk</hi> has got into the <hi>Infallible 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36442:11"/>Chair,</hi> he muſt be believed, there is no help, and we
muſt like the <hi>Welſh-man, Take her own word for it.</hi> And ſo let
him go away with all thoſe appoſite and choice Epithets he has given of
this <hi>moſt worthy</hi> and <hi>well-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> perſon, without
where, or when, or why, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; For I am ſure there is no way of
replying to them; and he that would ſet about it, might as well reſolve to
write an Anſwer to a Leaf in <hi>Textor</hi>'s Epithets.</p>
                  <p>And thus I have with much ado rid my hands of a great part of
<hi>De Cros</hi>'s Rubbiſh, as far as it endeavours to beſpatter Sir <hi>W.
T.</hi> in his Morals and Intellectuals. It remains now I ſhould obſerve a
little what he ſays con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Fortunes, which ſeems to turn upon
theſe two ruſty Hinges, that make as ill a noiſe as all the reſt; the
obſcurity from whence he was raiſed to all thoſe great Employments, and
his diſgrace upon leaving them, which <hi>De Cros</hi> ſays was immediately
after his Return from <hi>Nimeguen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my own part I muſt confeſs I am neither did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
nor have had Converſation in Courts, and with Publick Affairs, to give an
account how Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> came into Buſineſs, or how he went out, any
further than I could gather from Writings and Tranſactions which are publick
and known to every body; or by particular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries from ſome Friends and
Acquaintance of my own; and it has happened, that ſome of them have long
known ſo much of that Family, as to aſſure me it is a very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient one:
That Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> was born of a very Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Father, who was for many
years of the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil in <hi>Ireland</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> the
Firſt, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and was long poſſeſſed
of one of the beſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in that Kingdom, both for Honour and Profit; as
likewiſe in his time a Member of ſeveral Parliaments in <hi>England:</hi>
That his two younger Brothers are known to have lived always with plentiful
Fortunes, and in much eſteem: So that this Gentleman alone ſeems to have
been born under the unluckieſt Planet in the world, tho Heir to his Father's
Fortune, and Succeſſor to his <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36442:12"/>Office, which was ſo
conſiderable; yet he only of all his Family, was <hi>in Obſcurity,</hi> and
<hi>lay in the Duſt</hi> (for ſo the <hi>French</hi> Letter has it) till my
Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> raiſed him out of both; whoſe beams it ſeems were
ſo refulgent, as to make him ſhine at that diſtance his Foreign
Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments carried him to. My Friends have likewiſe aſſured me from
their own remembrance and knowledge, that Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> ſhined as much
in a Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſoon after the King's Reſtoration, as
<hi>De Cros</hi> ſays he ſhined long in his Employments abroad; and this
was ſeveral years before he came into any Foreign Employments. They told me
likewiſe that he was very eaſy in his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, not only by what he had
from his <hi>Father,</hi> but from his <hi>Lady,</hi> to whom God be thanked
(and it is very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for her Ladyſhip that) <hi>De Cros</hi> ſays, he has
no Quarrel. By all which, and the many Employments he ſince paſſed
through, and of which in one of his Eſſays he ſays, he <hi>never ſought
any;</hi> in my weak conception I ſhould think he was a perſon, that by the
Circumſtances of his Humour and his Fortune, needed the Court leſs than the
Court needed him.</p>
                  <p>As to his going out from Publick Employments, which <hi>De
Cros</hi> tells us was upon <hi>the King's being ſo ill ſatisfied with his
Conduct and Management of Affairs abroad, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly thoſe at</hi>
Nimeguen; that <hi>he ſlighted him upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from thence, and made
very little uſe of him.</hi> I can give no other Account beſides what I
find of the Time and the manner in the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> before the
<hi>Memoirs;</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I find, by comparing the Date of his Return from
<hi>Nimeguen,</hi> with that of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Declaration upon his
diſſolution of the old Council, and ſelecting a new one, that Sir <hi>W.
T.</hi> was a Member of that new and ſelect Council; and it was the Common
Town-talk at that time, that this Declaration was writ by him, and that he was
in his Majeſty's Chief Confidence upon that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing Reſolution,
which was received with ſuch Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes, Bonfires, and other
expreſſions of Joy in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Beſides all this, having had ſome
acquaintance among <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36442:12"/>
                     <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Merchants in Town, I
came to know, that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them about two years after, had recourſe to
Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> upon his being then declared Ambaſſador Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> by the King at Council, whereof he himſelf
was then a Member. All which laid together, does moſt abundantly verifie what
<hi>De Cros</hi> ſays of his being diſgraced upon his return from
<hi>Nime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen.</hi> But the beſt account of all theſe Paſſages we
muſt expect whenever he will think fit to publiſh the firſt and third
part of the <hi>Memoirs,</hi> which are mentioned at the beginning and end of
thoſe the world has ſeen already. In the mean time, what little has
happened to fall in the way of my knowledge or enquiries, may be enough to
diſcover the impudent Forgery of this falſe Coyner, who pretends to
counterfeit all ſorts of Metals, but is ſo wretched a bungler, and performs
it ſo groſly, that not one of them will paſs. 'Twas for this Reaſon, I
ſuppoſe, that the <hi>French</hi> Edition of his Letter pretends to have
been printed at <hi>Cologne,</hi> which I have long-obſerved to be the Common
Forge, or at leaſt the Common Form of Paltry, Scurrilous Libels, printed in
that Language; and which no Printer or Bookſeller abroad dare ſet their
Names to. This I cannot but mention for the Credit and Reputation of his
honeſt Stationer at the <hi>Mitre,</hi> who I believe is the only Stationer
in <hi>England</hi> would have had the ingenuity to ſet the <hi>Mitre</hi> on
this <hi>Monk's</hi> Head.</p>
                  <p>The laſt precious piece of his Malice I ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of, is That he grudges Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> even the Honour of his Retreat from
Publick Affairs, by which perhaps he has been more diſtinguiſhed, than by
his greateſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments: But this <hi>De Cros</hi> cannot allow him: No,
ſaye he, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>It was not what he would make us believe; his
love for his own eaſe, and his indiſpoſitions of body, that made him
decline his Employments.</hi> Alas! what a ſad Fate that man falls under,
that dares incur the diſpleaſure of Monſ. <hi>De Cros?</hi> or who can
tell what will become of him? He muſt neither live at Court, nor at his own
Houſe, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36442:13"/>Buſineſs, nor out of it; In Town,
nor in Country: where ſhall we find a place for him? I know none but the
middle Region of the Air: But, <hi>It was not his love for his own Eaſe,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>that made him decline his Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Why? whoever informed
this Conjurer it was? I am ſure the <hi>Memoirs</hi> ſay no ſuch thing,
but in the laſt Page gives us a quite different account; where, telling his
Reaſons why he excuſed himſelf, at his return from <hi>Nimeguen,</hi>
from entring upon the Secretaries Office, are theſe Words: <hi>I that never
had any thing ſo much at heart as the union of my Couutry, which I thought
the only way to its greatneſs and felicity was very unwilling to have any
part in the diviſions of it.</hi> And towards the end: <hi>After almoſt two
years unſucceſsful endeavours at ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or at leaſt ſome allay
of the Heats and Diſtempers between the King and his Parliaments, I took the
Reſolution of having no more to do with Affairs of State.</hi> Which
Reſolution it ſeems was taken about the beginning of the Year 1681. when he
ſent the King word he <hi>would paſs the remainder of his life like as good
a private Subject as any he had,</hi> &amp;c. as is to be ſeen in the
Epiſtle. Yet for all this Monſ. <hi>De Cros,</hi> who knows his thought
better than himſelf, or than his Actions can inform us, ſays, <hi>Never did
man deſire more to have a hand in Affairs.</hi> Why here he ſhews us the
ſilly <hi>Bubble</hi> again, and the wiſe way he takes to fulfil this
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient Deſire; 'Tis by going to his Houſe in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where he
ſtays five years, as he tells us in one of his Eſſays, without ſo much
as ever ſeeing the Town: and ſince (as I am inform'd) to avoid ſo much
Reſort at that ſmaller diſtance from the City, he goes to another of his
Houſes of a much greater in the Country; which was an admirable wiſe
Contrivance to ſatisfie his Longings to get again into Buſineſs: Truly I
my ſelf could have helpt him to a Better: For could he not like other men of
ſuch a craving Kidney, have ſtill buzzed about the Court, knocked at every
dore there, and when one was deaf and would not open, go to another; and at the
worſt have grown ſo troubleſome, that ſome body <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36442:13"/>would at laſt bring him into Employment; tho it were but to be rid
of him? Or, if this Contrivance had failed, he might have herded among the
Factious and Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented about the Town, gone to the Coffee houſes,
railed at the Miniſters, and quarrelled with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till they would
be glad to have hired him at the expence of an Employment to hold his Tongue:
And I am ſure if he talks as well as he writes, he might very well have gone
this way to work, and with as much likelihood to ſucceed as <hi>Others have
done, on pretend to do.</hi> Tho a Common Reader would be apt to think the
Author of theſe <hi>Memoirs</hi> might have found ſome other ways, either
of preſerving himſelf in Buſineſs, or of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in when he was out;
at leaſt in ſo eaſy a Court as that of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's
is taken to have been. Or if theſe Endeavours had miſcarried, he might yet
have made ſome ſhift or other to have obtained his Deſire upon ſuch a
Revolution as has ſince happened; and he is very much wronged by the common
Voice of the Town, if he has not found it as hard to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from
entring into Publick Employments in this Reign, as in that of the late King
<hi>Charles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my own part, I can profeſs with the greateſt Truth in
the world, That before this Libel of <hi>De Cros,</hi> I have never met with in
all my converſation and Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with the leaſt Reproach from any man
againſt Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> except it be in one point; Of his having made too
raſhly, or kept too obſtinately, his Reſolution, Never to enter again
into Publick Employments; eſpecially ſince he lives in an Age where ſuch
perſons as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be by his Writings, might be of ſo uncommon uſe
and Advantage to his Country: This I cannot but own, I have often heard laid,
and that ſomewhat warmly, to his charge, and muſt leave it to himſelf to
clear it as he can. But however, <hi>De Cros</hi> it ſeems knows his thoughts
beſt, and muſt be believed in all he ſays upon this Point, as well as the
reſt: And I only wiſh, ſince the Spark is <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36442:14"/>ſo good
at finding out what other men think, that he would take the pains to learn for
his comfort what all men think of him: One thing I am ſure is, that with all
the Bloaches of his dirty Pencil, he has daub'd up a Picture of Sir <hi>W.
T.</hi> which has top-fil'd the meaſure of all Forgery; <hi>Sed Vetitum nihil
eſt ſcheleri,</hi> and which is as true and like the Original, as a man
would make of this Dauber, if he ſhould ſay, <hi>De Cros</hi> were a very
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, worthy, well-natur'd, well-bred, fait-ſpoken, plain-dealing,
ingenious Writer; of excellent Morals, wondrous Wit, and exact Truth.</p>
                  <p>And now I have done with him, I can hardly anſwer it to my
ſelf why I ever began, or why I went about to foul my fingers with ſuch a
Subject: I am ſure nothing could have forced me but an irreſiſtible
Impulſe, and ſome natural love I bear to Vertue, to Learning, and to Truth;
of all which I find ſo great a ſhare in this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſon's
Writings, which I have read ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with ſo much pleaſure; and
from which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but confeſs to have learnt more than from all other
Books I have read in my life; which I ſay after much greater and better
Readers than my ſelf, and yet I have been a great Porer too. All this would
not ſuffer me to let <hi>De Cros</hi>'s Libel paſs without theſe
Reflections; for as to any regular Reply, it could no more be made to this,
than to a Paper that comes with a very fair Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription, and
ſubſcribed by ſome <hi>Worſhipful Name,</hi> but had nothing clear
through, beſides long unſightly Scrawls and foul Blots with a Pen; and ſo
intended for ſome ſuch flam as your Twelve-Penny Writers uſe to gull
thoſe idle people with, that buy up all Pamphlets they meet: And ſince I
have confeſs'd my ſelf ſuch a Cuſtomer, 'tis but juſtice I ſhould
be laughed at in my turn.</p>
                  <p>After all I have writ upon this Subject, I cannot but think my
Ink has been too white all this time; however, I have Gall enough about me to
make it blacker at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36442:14"/>if ever the fit of Scribling
ſhould take me again; which may very well be, when I meet with another
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſo little <hi>Wit,</hi> ſo little <hi>Memory,</hi> and ſo
little <hi>Truth</hi> as <hi>De. Cros.</hi> 
                     <q> 
                        <l>
                           <hi>— Melius non tangere, Clamo,</hi>
                        </l> 
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flebit, &amp; inſignis tota cantabitur
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to the candid Tranſlator, I cannot forbear doing him the
Juſtice to give him that part which he deſerves, and belongs to him in all
I ſaid of <hi>De Cros,</hi> for his ſhare in the Letter, by ſo falſe,
and ſo malicious a Tranſlation; nor can refuſe him my approbation for a
worthy Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator to ſo worthy an Author; wherein he has taken the ſame
pains a man would do in ſmutting over a Chimny-Sweeper, or blacking over a
Crier of Smalcoal. Which is all I ſhall ſay of him.</p>
                  <p>But, for the <hi>Advertiſer,</hi> as his Stile is much
fairer, and conſiſts moſtly of Criticiſms, ſo he will deſerve no
other than very fair and critical Reflections. Yet I cannot but wonder, that in
the firſt part of his Advertiſement, he ſhould go about to defend the
<hi>ſevere or indecent Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> (as he calls it) in <hi>De Cros</hi>'s
Letter: Which ſure, nothing could do towards a perſon who has ſo often
repreſented a great King, whatever his own Merits or Demerits might have
been. I am alſo ſomething at a loſs what he ſhould mean by ſlandering
<hi>De Cros</hi> with ſuch a Title as that of, <hi>The Ingenious Author of
the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letter.</hi> For doubtleſs if the Man has any Wit, I may ſay
of it as one did of a Gentleman's Courage, which another had much commended;
That <hi>he might have courage for ought he knew, but he had as live be damn'd
as ſhew it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The reſt of his gentle <hi>Advertiſement</hi>
conſiſts, (as he pleaſes to call it) of <hi>the Sentiments of the
Criticks upon theſe Memoirs when they firſt came out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36442:15"/>The firſt whereof is, That <hi>The Stile
was too luſcious and affected.</hi> I confeſs I am not acquainted with that
Term of <hi>a Luſcious Stile,</hi> and cannot eaſily ſtumble up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what
it means, unleſs it be to ſay, That the Bride is too fair, or the Grapes
are too ſweet. But 'tis yet harder for my poor Conception to find out how a
Stile can be both <hi>Luſcious</hi> and <hi>Affected;</hi> Which latter I
ſhould have otherwiſe miſtook for a Quality that had ever given a
harſhneſs to any Stile, that would not be very conſiſtent with
<hi>Luſcious:</hi> And <hi>Tacitus</hi> has not eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Imputation of
being both harſh and <hi>Affected,</hi> by ſeveral <hi>Criticks.</hi> I am
afraid the Gentleman's Mouth might have been a little out of taſte by reading
theſe <hi>Memoirs;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> might poſſibly have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
from ſome cholerick Humour redundant in his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach; which I the rather
ſuſpect from theſe words in the beginning of his Advertiſement; <hi>As
nothing more ſenſibly touches</hi> US, <hi>than no have our
Reputation,</hi> &amp;c. which ſeem to inſinuate, that he took himſelf
for one of the Perſons he thought offended by them, and <hi>treated with too
much Freedom, and too little Ceremony;</hi> as he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſpeaks of
others. But if Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s Stile be faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I have nothing to ſay;
only deſire, That ſome of the <hi>Criticks</hi> the <hi>Advertiſer</hi>
ſpeaks of, will be ſo kind to mend it when they write next, whereby I think
they will do a very great Honour to our Language. I am only ſorry for thoſe
poor Bookſellers who have ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undertaken the printing of his
ſeveral Works, and wiſh they may not be undone after the Judgment of
theſe ſevere <hi>Criticks</hi> upon them. Yet to give them a little
comfort, I muſt needs take notice, that all men are not of the ſame nice
Palat, neither at home nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: For Monſieur <hi>Wiquefort</hi> concludes
his <hi>Memoirs of Ambaſſadors,</hi> with regretting that there had been
ſo few Accounts given by any of them of Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; and that there
were like to be fewer hereafter; <hi>Becauſe Monſieur</hi> Temple <hi>is
inimitable in what he has <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36442:15"/>written of the United</hi>
Netherlands. And among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Books and Pamphlets that mention his Works, I have
yet ſeen none that does it without great Value and Approbation. I am ſure
in all the <hi>French</hi> Editions of his ſeveral Works (which have had the
luck to be ſtill Tranſlated into ſeveral Languages as they came out) the
Epiſtles and Prefaces prefixed before them, are full of the greateſt Honour
and Applauſe that can be given to Writings, which paſs ſo ill with the
<hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> this Advertiſer tells us of at home; ſo that 'tis
poſſible ſome of theſe <hi>Memoirs</hi> may yet go off, which I
ſuppoſe was the chief thing intended by him that publiſht them.</p>
                  <p>However, let ſuch Stateſmen as <hi>de Cros,</hi> or ſuch
<hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> as our <hi>Advertiſer,</hi> or Malice and Detraction it
ſelf, ſay what they will of the <hi>Memoirs;</hi> I dare anſwer for all
Scholars and Lovers of Learning, that they ſhall pay the Honour and Eſteem
which is, and will be ever juſtly due to the <hi>Miſcellanea;</hi> and
ſhall not only find what is pleaſing and inſtructing, but alſo
ſomething that is new and ſurprizing whenever they read them, let this
Author's Stile be as <hi>Luſcious</hi> and <hi>Affected</hi> as it will;
which is all I need ſay for the poor Bookſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler's ſake.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Criticiſm the Advertiſer mentions, is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Digreſſions, tho he is ſo good to confeſs himſelf not of their
Opinion who find ſault with them. But I wiſh he had made a fairer Quotation
in a Line or two out of one of them, by which he would ſeem to make Sir
<hi>W. T.</hi> ſay, That <hi>Prince</hi> Maurice's Parrot ſpoke, and askt,
and anſwered common Queſtions like a reaſonable Creature: Tho indeed he
only ſays, That his <hi>curioſity made</hi> him <hi>enquire from the
firſt hand about ſuch a common Story, Of a Parrot that ſpoke,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>For my ſelf, I muſt needs ſay, That that Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
gave me not only ſome Entertainment when I read it, but a good deal of
thought ſince; and the more, <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36442:16"/>becauſe I remember one of
the <hi>Athenian Mercuries,</hi> in Anſwer to a Queſtion ſent them upon
this very Story, ſeem'd to allow the thing poſſible. But after all my
rambling thoughts upon that Subject, I muſt leave it to better Reaſoners
than my ſelf to determine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Speech and Reaſon are ſo individual,
that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Creature has any ſhare in the one, muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to
partake of the other. However it be, the Letter I have been lately obſerving,
has throughly convinc'd me, that whether a Man may <hi>Speak</hi> or no, at
leaſt he may <hi>Write</hi> without <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But this I am ſure
is a Digreſſion in me, whatever it was in the Author of the
<hi>Memoirs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The laſt <hi>Criticiſm</hi> the <hi>Advertiſer</hi>
mentions, is, That <hi>in theſe</hi> Memoirs <hi>there are ſeveral
Perſons, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent both for their Station and Quality, and ſome of them
ſtill alive, treated with ſo much Freedom, and ſo little Ceremony.</hi>
This in my ſlender Judgment, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears a more extraordinary Objection, than
the other two. For I had ever imagined, that the very <hi>Ratio formalis</hi>
of a good Hiſtory, or Memoirs, had been the <hi>Truth</hi> of them, which it
is impoſſible ſhould ever appear without <hi>great Freedom,</hi> and
little Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, either to the Perſons they repreſent, or concerning the
Actions they relate. And this in my Opinion, gives the great and general
Eſteem that is deſervedly put upon the Memoirs of <hi>Philip de
Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> whoſe Stile ſeems very mean and vulgar, but his
<hi>Freedom</hi> great, and <hi>Ceremony</hi> very little, either with thoſe
two Great Princes that were his Maſters, or in any Account he gives of
Actions, or of Perſons, tho many of theſe were probably alive at the time
of Writing or Publiſhing theſe <hi>Memoirs.</hi> But in truth ſince his
time, his Method has been very little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and more is the pity, ſince
it has made ſo much room, and ſo unworthily, for the fulſome Flatteries, 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36442:16"/>and nauſeous Panegyricks of ſo many Books or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces
as have over-run the Preſs in our Age; which not only endeavour to put Shams
and Cheats up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mankind; but are, I doubt, of great Miſchief to the
Intereſts and Concernments of thoſe Countries where they grow. For let the
<hi>Criticks</hi> ſay what they pleaſe againſt writing Story with <hi>too
much Freedom,</hi> and <hi>too little Ceremony,</hi> I am a little diſpoſed
to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That if there were more ſuch <hi>Authors,</hi> there would not
be ſo many ſuch <hi>Actors,</hi> as have been ſo often ſeen upon the
Publick Stages of the World; who, like Rooks when they are gotten to the
Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branches of great Trees, think only of building their own Neſts as high
as they can, and feathering them as well as they can, without any care how the
Tree thrives under them, or whether by their Muting and Fluttering about, they
ſpoil the Branches and Leaves of that Tree it ſelf where they were bred, or
found ſhelter. Peradventure ſuch Actors would not have plaid ſuch Parts
upon the Stage, if they had not truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Diſguiſes and Masks they
were in, or had ſuſpected they would be pull'd off by ſome <hi>plain,
rough hand,</hi> either while the Play laſts, or as ſoon as 'tis ended. For
men are ſeldom ſo harden'd, as to grow totally careleſs of their Names,
and their Memories, after they are dead, tho they may hope to eſcape while
they are alive.</p>
                  <p>For theſe and ſome other ſuch trivial Reaſons, I
muſt profeſs, I cannot joyn heartily with the <hi>Criticks</hi> in this
laſt Objection; but ſhall be very glad to joyn with the Advertiſer in
believing, or at leaſt in wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> would be
prevailed with by the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or this Advertiſement, to take ſome notice
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf either of the one, or the other, which might poſſibly make the
Preſs ſome amends for this Scribble of mine; at leaſt it would me, who
ſhould think my <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36442:17"/>ſelf very well rewarded by it. For
whatever Paſſion <hi>de Cros,</hi> or the <hi>Advertiſer,</hi> or any of
thoſe US's he ſpeaks of in the beginning of his ſhort Paper, may have
againſt the Author, I ſhall ever have as much Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his
Writings. And as for this of my own, I pretend to no more, than to be forgiven
by him and other Men, becauſe it is my firſt Eſſay, and for ought I yet
know, it may be my laſt.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36442:17"/>
                  <p>REFLECTIONS UPON AN ANSWER TO THE Letter from Monſ. <hi>De
Cros.</hi> Pretended to be written by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Memoirs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By a Lover of Truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near
the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1693.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36442:18"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:36442:18"/>
                  <head>REFLECTIONS upon an Anſwer to the Letter from Monſieur
<hi>De Cros.</hi> Pretended to be written by the Author of the
<hi>Memoirs,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>WHEN the foregoing Papers were finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and juſt ready
for the Preſs, I was ſurprized to hear that Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
had thought fit (contrary to what I had conjectured in the firſt pages of
thoſe) to take publick notice of Monſ. <hi>De Cros</hi>'s Letter; That it
was now juſt come out, and crying about the Streets: Tho I had then ſeveral
ſurmiſes that it might be ſome Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, yet one could not well be
more amazed than I was, as a piece of News I had ſo little expected, and the
contrary of which I thought I had ſo well convinced both the world, and my
ſelf. Whatever I expected from it, I was eager enough to get it, and to read
it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: My ſuſpicion increaſed ſufficiently, when I had not gone
above ten Lines; and when I had peruſed it, I found my ſelf as much
diſappointed, as I was by <hi>De Cros</hi>'s Letter; being throughly
convinced it was a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, (tho a witty one, and perhaps an innocent one
too.) For this I found ſeveral undeniable Reaſons, which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any
thinking Reader could not but obſerve as well as I.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, I took notice of the <hi>Exordium</hi> as a
little too common and thredbare for that Author; and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a worſe Writer
might have been hard put to it, not to have found a better than, The
<hi>importunity of his Friends</hi> for writing in his own defence. Beſides,
I thought the diſguiſe of it was ſomething mean, and could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
why, if that Author had a mind to own it, he <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36442:19"/>ſhould
chuſe to do it in the <hi>Third Perſon,</hi> rather than the
<hi>Firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another Reaſon is; That this Anſwerer makes him publickly
own the <hi>Memoirs,</hi> which I could never hear he has yet done. Nay
farther; He makes Him defend them in all parts; which I doubt, if he had owned
them, he would not do it any further than the Truth; ſince for the reſt, as
the Publiſher of them obſerves, they are in many places imperfect, and
uncorrect, by having never been reviewed; and ſo may be juſtly liable to
ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of that kind: And the <hi>Galliciſms</hi> upon which
<hi>De Cros</hi>'s <hi>Advertiſer</hi> ſays, the <hi>Criticks</hi> have
been ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, may eaſily diſcover they were not deſigned for the
Publick in that Dreſs they have appeared. Now, tho this Pretended Anſwerer
endeavours to imitate Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> in this Point, as well as in the uſe
of ſeveral other Words which are found in the <hi>Memoirs,</hi> and he
imagines a little particular; yet he has made ſo great a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in
ſeveral others, that by conſiſting of two ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent pieces, the
whole lies too open to deceive. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho ſuch words as <hi>Blunder,
Hanſ-en Kelder, A man of ſuch a Kidney</hi> with ſome others, may well
enough become ſuch a Scribler as I am, yet they are very unlike that
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Expreſſions, and below his Stile.</p>
                  <p>Another ground I have to conclude this Anſwer for a
Counterfeit, is for ſome Quotations which I ſhall never ſuſpect ſuch
a Writer as Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> would have made uſe of. As firſt, that poor
Line, <hi>Canes qui latrant,</hi> &amp;c. which looks like an
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb tranſlated into very bald <hi>Latin.</hi> Then (to
mention no more of them) another Quotation as unlike as the firſt, from Mr.
<hi>Samuel Johnſon,</hi> which agrees very little with that Author's way, who
is obſerved in all he writes, to be very tender in medling with controverted
Points of State and Government.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, This whole Pamphlet, tho it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd
to be ingenious, and written with a great deal of Wit, yet that very ſtrain
of <hi>Witting</hi> it ſo much, and running things into Ridicule, makes it
look very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36442:19"/>from any thing we have yet ſeen of
Sir <hi>W. T</hi>'s Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: And I obſerve in ſeveral places of the
<hi>Miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea,</hi> this very vein is taken notice of for a thing of
<hi>pernicious Conſequence to Learning and good Manners;</hi> ſo that if
Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> be really poſſeſſed of ſuch a Talent, he keeps it
very much to himſelf, and muſt be allowed for the beſt Diſguiſer of
it in the World, through all he had publiſhed; which would make his Readers
think that he intended to paſs rather for a Wife and Good Man, than for a
Witty.</p>
                  <p>Another ſufficient Reaſon for me to reject this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
is, That it makes Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> grant in ſome kind, the ſevereſt of
<hi>de Cros</hi>'s unreaſonable Slanders, of <hi>failing in his Fidelity to
his Maſter;</hi> and to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in it, by excuſing it from
Examples of that kind; which in my Opinion, would be to lay himſelf
need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly open to Cenſures, that I ſuppoſe, he has not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved;
and would ſhew ſuch a want of Judgment in him, as I ſhall not be apt to
believe from and other Writings but his own, and better atteſted than I find
it here.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall add to all theſe, what I obſerved in an
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement before the Firſt Part of the <hi>Miſcellanea,</hi> where
the Bookſeller tells the Reader from the Author, that thenceforth he would
never Publiſh any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting his Name to it, which not finding
before this Pamphlet, was another Reaſon to conclude it a ſuppoſititious
Piece. All which put together, makes me believe Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> was no more
the Author of this Anſwer, than of <hi>Tully</hi>'s <hi>Offices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I had ſatisfied my ſelf in this Point, it was not
eaſy for me to find out what the Writer of this Anſwer ſhould mean by
taking ſo much pains to make it paſs for Sir <hi>W. T.</hi>'s; which
ſeems to me a very new way of Writing; and whereof I cannot give any other
inſtance beſides this, from what has occured in my Reading or
Converſation. I know very well, that ſeveral Ancient Pieces which go under
great Author's <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36442:20"/>Names, are found by the Learned Criticks of
theſe latter Ages, to have been ſpurious; yet they were never born till
long after the Death of the ſuppoſed Fathers. I know likewiſe, that there
have been ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Laws made in <hi>France;</hi> one, I am ſure, in this
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Century, againſt the Printing any Books, under ſevere Penalties,
without ſetting the Author's Name to them, and their known Name, becauſe
ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving two Names, one by which they were commonly called, tho the other
perhaps were the particular Name of their Family; ſome Perſons
diſguiſed their Writings under the Name that was little known, tho it might
be their own: To ſo nice and cautious Cares the Laws there thought fit to
deſcend upon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I remember there was an Ingenious Diſcourſe
Printed within theſe few years in <hi>France,</hi> upon the Cuſtom of
uſing borrowed or diſguiſed Names in the Publiſhing of Books: But in
the Cenſures and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints that Author makes of this ill Cuſtom, I did
not take notice of any one Example he mentions, further than of ſuch Books as
had been publiſhed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Names of Perſons dead, or elſe under ſuch as
were wholly fictitious, and made at their own pleaſures; which laſt has
peradventure appear'd in moſt Ages and Countries where Printing has been
uſed, but toucht no Man farther than a Satyr of <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> or
<hi>Francion,</hi> or any ſuch like. But I have never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, nor heard
of any Example of this kind beſides this Anſwer, where the Auther, whole
Name was bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, was alive, and in the ſame Kingdom, and ſo avowedly
with the Name of a known Bookſeller in the Title-page.</p>
                  <p>Whatever the intention may have been in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whether
wholly innocent, or a little intereſſed to give Vogue to his Pamphlet, or
in conſidering the Bookſeller's profit by making it paſs for an Author's,
whoſe Name he knew would <hi>help it off the</hi> better; yet I cannot but
apprehend the Example of it ill, and <pb n="39" facs="tcp:36442:20"/>the Conſequences of
it may be worſe, if it ſhould fall into Common practice; for by this way of
Writing and Publiſhing either Books or Pamphlets, any Man may be made a
publick Defamer of himſelf at another Man's pleaſure, and not only
<hi>ſo,</hi> but to accuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of any Crime which the Rigour of our
Laws requires no man to do. As far as my Thoughts will reach, I do not conceive
why it ſhould not be as bad to counterfeit a Book as a Bond; and to wrong a
Man in his Reputation, as great an Injury, as to cheat him of his Money: This
muſt be the reaſon why Slander and Scandal are as ſufficient a ground to
maintain an Action in Law, as Damage and Battery: Nothing is an injury any
farther than it is taken, and hurts a Man more or leſs, as he is ſenſible
of it, Now, tho it may be true, that in every Age there may be more than
<hi>Nine Worthies</hi> who put a greater value on their Money than their
Honour, yet there may be every where, and at all times, ſome <hi>ſilly
Foplings,</hi> who do quite the contrary; and I know no reaſon, why they
ſhould not pretend to be ſafe in the Poſſeſſions they moſt value,
as well as the others; nor why the Law ſhould not take fome care of ſuch
poor Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents. Nor further, can I find out why a <hi>Stationer</hi> ſhould
not be puniſht for <hi>Forgery,</hi> as well as a <hi>Notary</hi> or
<hi>Scrivener</hi> may be. Whether I am too ſerious or no, upon a Subject
that may appear trivial at firſt ſight, or whether ſuch a Trifle be worth
any legal Proviſions againſt it, I am ſure, <hi>Hae Nugae ſeria ducunt
in Mala;</hi> and that 'tis at leaſt an <hi>Edg-tool</hi> which ought not to
be plaid with.</p>
                  <p>I could never well comprehend the true reaſon, why it
ſhould be ſuch a diſgrace to be a <hi>Cuckold,</hi> or why one Perſon
ſhould ſuffer for another's fault, how near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoever related to him: But
I can very eaſily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Injury of it, which is, that one Man
ſhould be put upon fathering another Man's Children, or at the beſt
ſhould be in danger of it; and this ſeems to be <pb n="40" facs="tcp:36442:21"/>meant
by the word, which at firſt was intended, that a Man was <hi>Cuckoo'd,</hi>
that is, dealt with as <hi>Cuckoos</hi> are ſaid to do with other Birds, by
laying their Eggs in their Neſts, and thereby making them hatch and bring up
young Ones that are none of their own, (for this is the beſt Etymology I can
find out for a word ſo commonly uſed). Now, the ſame Injury may be as
ſenſible in what concerns the Children of the Brain (as Books have been
call'd) which may be as lawful and as natural Iſſues, and ſome parents
may be as fond of them, and as much concerned about them. And tho it paſs for
no Crime for People to expoſe their Children when they have no mind to own
them, or think they are not able to maintain them, and they may be content any
body elſe ſhould father them that will; yet this is an Office no body would
be forc'd upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, how little ſoever it may coſt them, and how
innocently ſoever it may have been intended.</p>
                  <p>I could not forbear to make this Reflection upon this Subject,
if it were for nothing elſe but to make good my Profeſſion in the
Title-page, of being <hi>A Lover of Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
